<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
 <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Account of a Voyage up the River de la Plata, and thence over land to Peru
           With Observations on the Inhabitants, as well Indians and Spainards, the Cities, Commerce, Fertility, and Riches of that Part of America</title>
                       <author>Mons. Acarete du Biscay</author>
            <editor>Busa's Enthusiasts</editor>

        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
         <p><ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Released under a Creative Commons BY-NC-SA License</ref></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
        <p>
           <bibl>
         <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
         <publisher> Printed for S. Bucklet </publisher>
         <date> 1698 </date>  
         </bibl>
         </p>
        </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="eng">
   <body>
   <pb/>
   <head>Monsieur Acarete du Biscay's Journey from Buenos Ayres to Peru.</head>
     <div>
     <pb n="24"/>
      <fw type="head">24 A Voyage to Peru</fw>
          <p>
I Left <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>, and took the Road to<lb/> <name type="place"><orig>Cordoua</orig></name>, leaving <name type="place" ref= "https://whgazetteer.org/places/13634082/portal">Santa Fe</name> on 
my<lb/> right hand, of which place take this ac<lb/>count, <sic>'tis</sic> a Spanish Settlement 
dependant<lb/> upon <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>, the Commander is<lb/> no more than a <name type="personRoleName">Lieutenant</name>, 
and does no<lb/>thing but by order from the <name type="personRoleName">Governor</name><lb/> of <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>. <sic>'Tis</sic> a 
little place con<lb/>taining 25 Houses, without any Walls, Fortifications, or 
Garrison, distant 80<lb/> Leagues from <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name> Northward,<lb/> Situate upon the 
<name type="place">River de la Plata</name>, large<lb/> Vessels might come up to it, were it not<lb/> for a 
great bank that obstructs the pas<lb/>sage a little above <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>. 
Ne<lb/>vertheless <sic>'tis</sic> a very advantageous Post,<lb/> because <sic>'tis</sic> the only passage 
from <name type="place">Peru</name>,<lb/> <name type="place">Chili</name> and <name type="place" ref= "https://whgazetteer.org/places/13022580/portal">Tucuman</name> to <name type="place">Paraguay</name>, and in<lb/> a manner the Magazine of 
the Commodi<lb/>
<fw type="catch">ties.</fw> 
 <pb n="25"/>
         <fw type="head">up the <name type="place">R. de la Plata</name> 25</fw>
ties drawn from thence, particularly that<lb/> Herb already spoken 
of, which they<lb/> cannot be without in those Provinces.<lb/> The Soil is as good 
and Fertile here as<lb/> at <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>; and the Town having<lb/> nothing 
remarkably different from what<lb/> has been <sic>observ'd</sic> of <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>, I<lb/> leave 
it, and proceed upon my Jour<lb/>ney. <sic>'Tis</sic> counted 140 Leagues from<lb/> <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos 
<orig>Ayres</orig></name> to <name type="place" ref= "https://whgazetteer.org/places/13803619/portal"><orig>Cordoua</orig></name>, and because<lb/> some parts of the Road are uninhabited<lb/> for a 
long way together; I surnished<lb/> my self at my departure with what I<lb/> was 
<sic>inform'd</sic> I should stand in need<lb/> of; so I set out having a Savage for my<lb/> 
Guide, with Three Horses and Three<lb/> Mules, some to carry my Baggage, and<lb/> 
the rest to change upon the way when<lb/> that I rid upon was tired.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
From Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig>, to the River Lu<lb/>can, and even as far as the <name type="place">River 
Recife</name>,<lb/> 30 Leagues, I <sic>pass’d</sic> by several Habita<lb/>tions and Farms cultivated 
by the <name type="org">Spani<lb/>ards</name>, but beyond <name type="place" ref="https://www.getty.edu/vow/TGNFullDisplay?find=&amp;place=&amp;nation=&amp;english=Y&amp;subjectid=1019176">Recife</name> to the <name type="place" ref="https://www.getty.edu/vow/TGNFullDisplay?find=&amp;place=&amp;nation=&amp;english=Y&amp;subjectid=1019962">River<lb/> Salladillo</name>, I saw none. 
Let it be obser<lb/>ved by the way, that these Rivers as well<lb/> as all the rest 
in the Provinces of <name type="place" ref="https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>, <name type="place" ref="https://www.getty.edu/vow/TGNFullDisplay?find=&amp;place=&amp;nation=&amp;english=Y&amp;subjectid=1000055">Paraguay</name> and <name type="place" ref="https://www.getty.edu/vow/TGNFullDisplay?find=&amp;place=&amp;nation=&amp;english=Y&amp;subjectid=1001579">Tucuman</name>, that fall<lb/> into the 
<name type="place">River de la Plata</name> are fordable on Horse-back; but when the Rains or<lb/> 
<fw type="catch">any</fw> 
     <pb n="26"/>
      <fw type="head">26 A Voyage to Peru</fw>
any other accident swells them, a Tra<lb/>veller must either swim over, or else get<lb/> 
upon a bundle in the nature of a raft,<lb/> which a <rs type="otherness">Savage</rs> hawls over to the 
other<lb/> side. I could not Swim, and so was<lb/> <sic>forc'd</sic> to make use of this 
expedient<lb/> twice or thrice when I could not find a<lb/> Ford. The way was this, 
my <rs type="caste">Indian<lb/></rs> <sic>kill'd</sic> a Wild Bull, flead the Hide off,<lb/> stuffed it with straw, 
and <sic>ty'd</sic> it up in<lb/> a great bundle with thongs of the same<lb/> Hide, upon which 
I <sic>plac'd</sic> my self with<lb/> my Baggage ; he swam over hawling me<lb/> after him by a 
Cord <sic>ty'd</sic> to the bundle,<lb/> and then he <sic>repass'd</sic> and swam my Horses<lb/> and Mules 
over to me.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
All the Country between the <name type="place">River<lb/> Recife</name> and <name type="place" ref= "https://whgazetteer.org/places/13099083/portal">Salladillo</name>, <sic>tho'</sic> uninhabited,<lb/> 
abounds in Cattle and all sorts of Fruit-<lb/>trees, except Walnut and Chesnut-<lb/>
trees; there are whole Woods of Nectarine-<lb/>Trees, Three or Four Leagues in 
compass,<lb/> that bear excellent Fruit, which they<lb/> not only eat raw, but bake 
them, or dry<lb/> them in the Sun, to keep, as we in France<lb/> do Prunes: They 
seldom use any other<lb/> than the Wood of this Tree for common<lb/> firing at 
<name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>, and thereabouts.<lb/> The Savages that dwell in these Parts are<lb/> 
distinguish'd into two sorts, those that<lb/> 
<fw type="catch">volun-</fw> 
 <pb n="27"/>
         <fw type="head">up the R. de la Plata 27</fw>
voluntarily submit to the <rs type="caste">Spaniards</rs> are<lb/> call’d <foreign><orig><rs type="otherness">Panpistas</rs></orig></foreign>, the rest <foreign><rs type="caste">Serranos</rs></foreign>, both<lb/> cloathed with 
Skins, but the last set up<lb/>on the <rs type="otherness"><orig>Panpistas</orig></rs> as their mortal Enemies<lb/> 
wherever they meet with them. All<lb/> Fight on Horse-back, either with Lances<lb/> 
pointed with Iron or Bones sharpen'd,<lb/> or else with Bows and Arrows, they<lb/> 
wear Bulls-hides fashion'd like a Doublet<lb/> without sleeves, to defend their 
Bodies.<lb/> Their Chiefs that command over them<lb/> in War and Peace, are call’d 
<orig>Couracas</orig>.<lb/> When they take any one of their Ene<lb/>mies, alive or dead, they 
meet all toge<lb/>ther, and after they have reproach'd him,<lb/> that either he or 
his Relations were the<lb/> death of their Kindred or Friends, they<lb/> cut and 
tear him into pieces, which they<lb/> roast a little and eat, making a drinking<lb/> 
Bowl of his Scull. They feed mostly<lb/> upon flesh either raw or dress'd, and<lb/> 
particularly Colts flesh, which they like<lb/> better than Veal. They catch 
abundance<lb/> of Fish likewise in their Rivers, They<lb/> have no settled places of 
aboad, but<lb/> ramble up and down, several Families<lb/> together, and live in 
Tents.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
I could not inform my self exactly<lb/> what Religion they were of, but I was<lb/> 
told that they look'd upon the Sun and<lb/> 
<fw type="catch">Moon</fw> 
     <pb n="28"/>
      <fw type="head">28 A Voyage to Peru</fw>
Moon as Deities and as I travell'd along,<lb/> I saw a Savage upon his knees with his<lb/> Face to the Sun, who cry'd 
out and<lb/> made strange gestures with his Hands<lb/> and Arms. I learn'd from the 
Savage that<lb/> accompany'd me, that he was one of<lb/> those they call'd <rs type="ReligOrder">Papas</rs>, 
who in the<lb/> Morning kneel towards the Sun, and at<lb/> Night towards the Moon, 
to supplicate<lb/> those fancy'd Divinities to be propitious<lb/> to them, to give 
them fair Weather, and<lb/> Victory over their Foes.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
They make no great Ceremony in<lb/> their Marriages ; but when a Relation<lb/> dies, 
after they have rubb’d his body<lb/> with a certain Earth that consumes all but<lb/> 
the Bones, they preserve them, and carry<lb/> as many of them as they can 
convenient<lb/>ly about with them in a sort of Chests,<lb/> and this they do in 
token of their af<lb/>fection to their Kindred ; indeed they<lb/> are not wanting in 
good Offices to them<lb/> during their Lives, nor in their Sickness<lb/> and Death.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
Along the <name type="place">River Salladillo</name>, I took<lb/> notice of a great many Parrats, or 
<orig>Pa<lb/>pagays</orig>, as the <name type="org">Spaniards</name> call them, and<lb/> certain Birds, call’d 
<foreign>Guacamayos</foreign>, whic<lb/> are of divers Colours, and twice or thrice<lb/> as big as a 
Parrat. The River it self is<lb/> 
<fw type="catch">full-</fw> 
 <pb n="29"/>
         <fw type="head">up the R. de la Plata 29</fw>
full of the Fish, call'd Dorado, which is<lb/> very good to eat. There is also a Crea<lb/>ture in it, whether 'tis Meat or 
<sic>Poyson</sic><lb/> no body knows, it has Four Feet and a<lb/> long Tail like a Lizard.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
From <name type="place" ref= "https://whgazetteer.org/places/13099083/portal">Salladillo</name> quite to <name type="place"><orig>Cordoua</orig></name>, you<lb/> go along a very fine River, that 
abounds<lb/> with Fish, which is neither wide nor<lb/> deep, for it may be forded 
over. On<lb/> the Bank of it you meet with little Plan<lb/>tations every Three or 
Four Leagues ;<lb/> which are like Country Houses inhabi<lb/>ted by <rs type="caste">Spaniards</rs>, 
<rs type="caste">Portuguese</rs>, and the <rs type="people">Na<lb/>tives</rs>, who have all the necessary acco<lb/>modations of 
Life they can wish, and<lb/> are very Civil and Charitable to Stran<lb/>gers; their 
principal Wealth is in Hor<lb/>ses and Mules, in which they Trade with<lb/> the 
Inhabitants of <name type="place">Peru</name>.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
<orig><name type="place">Cordoua</name></orig> is a Town Situate in a pleasant<lb/> and fruitful Plain upon the side 
of a<lb/> River, bigger and broader than that I<lb/> have just spoken of : 'Tis 
compos’d of<lb/> about 400 Houses, Built like those of<lb/> <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>. It has 
neither Ditches,<lb/> nor Walls, nor Fort for its defence; He<lb/> that Commands it 
is Governor of all<lb/> the Provinces of <name type="place">Tucuman</name>, and tho’ it be<lb/> the place of 
his ordinary Residence, yet<lb/> he is wont now and then, as he sees oc<lb/>
<fw type="catch">casion,</fw> 
     <pb n="30"/>
      <fw type="head">30 A Voyage to Peru</fw>
casion, to go and pass some time at <orig>St.<lb/> <name type="place">Jago de l’Estro</name></orig>, at <name type="place">St. Miguel de Tucuman</name>,<lb/> 
(which is theCapitalCity of theProvince)<lb/> at <name type="place">Salta</name> and at <name type="place">Xuxui</name>. In each 
of these<lb/> Villages there is a  <name type="personRoleName">Lieutenant</name>, who has<lb/> under him an Alcalde and 
some Officer<lb/> for the Administration of Justice. The<lb/> <name type="personRoleName">Bishop</name> of <name type="place">Tucuman</name> 
likewise usually re<lb/>sides at <orig><name type="place">Cordoua</name></orig>, where the Cathedral<lb/> is the only 
Parish Church of the whole<lb/> Town ; but there are divers Convents of<lb/> Monks, 
namely of <rs type="ReligOrder">Dominican</rs>, Recol<lb/>lects, and those of the <orig>Order de la Mer<lb/>cy</orig>: and 
one of Nunns. The <rs type="ReligOrder">Jesuits</rs><lb/> have a College there, and their Chappel<lb/> is the 
finest and richest of all.<lb/>
</p>
<p>
The Inhabitants are Rich in Gold and<lb/> Silver, which they get by the Trade<lb/> 
they have for Mules, with which they<lb/> furnish <name type="place">Peru</name> and other Parts; which 
is<lb/> so considerable, that they sell about 28<lb/> or 30000 of 'em every Year, 
which they<lb/> breed up in their Farms. They usually<lb/> keep 'em till they are 
about Two Years<lb/> old, then expose 'em to Sale, and have<lb/> about Six Patagons 
a piece for 'em.<lb/> The Merchants that come to buy 'em, carry<lb/> 'em to <name type="place">St. 
Jago</name>, to <name type="place">Salta</name> and <name type="place">Xuxui</name> ,<lb/> where they leave 'em for Three Years,<lb/> till they 
are well grown and become<lb/> 
<fw type="catch">strong,-</fw> 
 <pb n="31"/>
         <fw type="head">up the R. de la Plata 31</fw>
strong, and afterwards bring 'em to name <name type="place">Pe<lb/>ru</name>, where 
they presently have Vent for<lb/> 'em, because there as well as in the rest<lb/> of 
the Western part of <name type="place">America</name>, the<lb/> greatest part of their Carriage is upon<lb/> 
Mules. The People of <name type="place"><orig>Cordoua</orig></name> also<lb/> drive a Trade in Cows, which they have<lb/> 
from the <sic>Countrey</sic> of <name type="place" ref= "https://www.hgis-indias.net/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=gazetteer:9000001">Buenos <orig>Ayres</orig></name>, and<lb/> carry to <name type="place">Peru</name>, where without this 
way<lb/> of Subsistance 'tis certain they would<lb/> have much ado to live. This 
kind of<lb/> <sic>Traffick</sic> makes this Town the most con<lb/>siderable in the <name type="place">Province of 
Tucuman</name>,<lb/> as well for its Riches and Commodities,<lb/> as for the Number of its 
Inhabitants,<lb/> which are counted to be at least 5 or 600 Families, besides 
Slaves who are<lb/> three times the number. But the gene<lb/>rality of 'em of all 
degrees have no other<lb/> Arms but a Sword and Poignard, and<lb/> are very 
indifferent <sic>Souldiers</sic>, the Air<lb/> of the Country, and the Plenty they<lb/> enjoy, 
rendring them Lazy and Cowardly.<lb/>
          </p>
     </div>
     </body>
 </text>
</TEI>